Guide to the Robin Kirk Papers, 1968-2012 and undated, bulk 1983-1994 RL.11761
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robin Kirk papers
1968-2012 and undated
1983-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kirk, Robin
RL.11761
13.8 Linear Feet
Robin Kirk is the Faculty co-chair of the Duke University Human Rights Center at the Franklin Humanities Institute. At the time these files were created, Kirk was serving both as a journalist and a Human Rights Watch researcher. Subject files include notes; research materials; newspaper clippings, magazines; reports, many from human rights organizations; correspondence; copies of governmental documents; notebooks; and other items on human rights, primarily in Peru. There are small amounts of material related to Colombia, Haiti and the Dominican Republic, Ecuador, and Bolivia. Publications primarily address politics and human rights issues, particularly in Colombia.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Subject files and publications.
Biographical / Historical
Robin Kirk is the Faculty co-chair of the Duke University Human Rights Center at the Franklin Humanities Institute and is a founding member of the Pauli Murray Project, an initiative of the center that seeks to use the legacy of this Durham daughter to examine the region's past of slavery, segregation and continuing economic inequality. An author and human rights advocate, Kirk is a lecturer in the Department of Cultural Anthropology and directs the Human Rights Certificate. An essayist and award-winning poet, she has published widely on issues as diverse as the Andes, torture, the politics of memory, family life and pop culture. Kirk authored, co-authored and edited over twelve reports for Human Rights Watch. In the 1980s, Kirk reported for U.S. media from Peru, where she covered the war between the government and the Shining Path. She continues to write for US media, and has been published in The New York Times, Washington Post, Sojourners, The American Scholar, the Raleigh News and Observer, the Boston Globe, the Durham Herald Sun and other media.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Robin Kirk Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Collection Overview
Subject files include notes; research materials; newspaper clippings, magazines; reports, many from human rights organizations; correspondence; copies of governmental documents; notebooks; and other items on human rights, primarily in Peru. There are small amounts of material related to Colombia, Haiti and the Dominican Republic, Ecuador, and Bolivia. At the time these files were created, Kirk was serving both as a journalist and a Human Rights Watch researcher. Publications primarily address politics and human rights issues, particularly in Colombia.
Human Rights -- Perú -- History -- 20th century; Human Rights -- Colombia.; Human Rights -- Haiti.; Human Rights -- Dominican Republic; Human Rights -- Ecuador; Human Rights -- Bolivia; Peru -- History -- 1980-; Colombia -- Politics and government; Colombia -- History; Haiti -- History; Dominican Republic -- History -- 20th century; Ecuador -- History -- 20th century; Bolivia -- History -- 20th century; Kirk, Robin; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Subject files, 1983-2008 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Subject files include notes; research materials; newspaper clippings, magazines; reports, many from human rights organizations; correspondence; copies of governmental documents; notebooks; and other items on human rights, primarily in Peru. There are small amounts of material related to Colombia, Haiti and the Dominican Republic, Ecuador, and Bolivia. At the time these files were created, Kirk was serving both as a journalist and a Human Rights Watch researcher.
  - Peru
    - Peru News- Pre 1988, undated (Box 1)
    - Women Rape in EZ until 1992, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Women Threats by Security Forces, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Rape Background Cases, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Gustavo Gutierrez Interview, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Ayacucho- Latin American Examiner, 1987 (Box 1)
    - A Minga of God, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Democracy and Terror, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Refugees- Chicago, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Gulag- La Cantuta (Box 2)
    - Cantuta, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Celia Valenzuela, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Gulag- Assante Alfano, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Gulag- Bonifacio Aymitumi, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Martin Roca, 1994 (Box 2)
    - [Human Rights Watch], 1994-1996 (Box 2)
    - Drugs, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Shining Path Attacks (Pre 1991), 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - "Narcotrafico: a un año de cartegena", 1991 (Box 2)
    - Internal Refugees, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Human Rights, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Cholera, Undated (Box 2)
    - AFSC Meeting, April 25, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Peru HR, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Human Rights (Pre-1991), 1990 (Box 2)
    - Peru Shantytowns, Undated (Box 2)
    - Coca (Pre-1991), 1990 (Box 2)
    - Universities, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - [Functional Annual Plan of Peru], 1991 (Box 2)
    - Desplazados 1980's, Undated (Box 2)
    - Accomarca, 1992 (Box 2)
    - UN Actions, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Promotion, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Gulag- La Encañada, Undated (Box 2)
    - Contracts, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Senderology, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - US-Peru Relations, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Misc., 1991 (Box 2)
    - [Fujimori Speech], Undated (Box 2)
    - Gulag Judicial System, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Gulag- Arrepentidos, 1994 (Box 2)
    - [Shining Path Trials], 1994 (Box 2)
    - Universidad del Centro, 1992 (Box 3)
    - CCD Investigation, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Robles, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Gulag-Salinas, Undated (Box 3)
    - Amnesty International, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Constitución Politica del Peru, Undated (Box 3)
    - Amnesty, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Weird Letters, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - Contracts, Peru Scholars, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Polica, 1993 (Box 3)
    - News, Birthcontrol, and Aborition, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Auca Yacu Huanuco, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Journalists, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Prison/Motives, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Misc. Cases 1, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Gulag Related HR, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Misc. Cases 2, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - Internal Refugees, 1993 (Box 3)
    - [La Republica Quotes], Undated (Box 3)
    - La Repiticion de Violencia, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Death Penalty, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Gulag- Chuchon-Salcedo, Undated (Box 3)
    - [Cursos para Oficiales], 1992 (Box 3)
    - [Carceleta Judicial de Lima], 1993 (Box 3)
    - Reporte Especial #13, 1993 (Box 3)
    - [Consejo Supremo de Justicia Militar], 1993 (Box 3)
    - Human Rights #1, 1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Church, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Raguel Martin Case, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Fuji Coup- US-Peru Relations, 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - AW Case Letters/State, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Gulag- Wagner, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Gulag- Sarasota Layme B, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Trip- Arcila/Susana, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Indigenous, 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Gulag- Correspondence, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Gulag- Santa Barbra, 1994 (Box 4)
    - [Publications], 1991-1995; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Coca, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - UA's, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Untitled, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Human Rights #2, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Reaño, Jose Miguel, Undated (Box 4)
    - San Ignacio, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Gov't Pronouncements/Laws, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - AW Case Letters/Statements, 1993 (Box 5)
    - [Publications], 1989 (Box 5)
    - HR, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - [Publications], 1989 (Box 5)
    - [Violencia Domestica], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Publications], 1993-1995 (Box 5)
    - [Publications], 1993-2008 (Box 5)
    - [Publications], 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Notebook 3, Undated (Box 5)
    - Phone Book, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 5)
    - Notebook 5, Undated (Box 5)
    - Notebook 10, Undated (Box 5)
    - Notebook 11, Undated (Box 5)
    - Notebook 13, Undated (Box 6)
    - Notebook 14, Undated (Box 6)
    - [President Gonzalo Speeches], Undated (Box 6)
    - Interview to Chairman Gonzalo, Undated (Box 6)
    - Exchanges with SL, 1987-1992 (Box 6)
    - Stone, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Exchanges with SP, 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - Justice, 1986-1987 (Box 6)
    - Rep., 1992-1995 (Box 6)
    - Refugees- PCR Reports, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Peru's Dirty Little War, 1987 (Box 6)
    - Women, SP Biblio, Undated (Box 6)
    - Women- Rape in interrogation until 1992, 1983-1992 (Box 6)
    - Drugczar Notebook, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Spike Notebook, Undated (Box 6)
    - Al Conference, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Untitled Notebook, 2002 (Box 6)
    - Calendar Notebook, 1993 (Box 6)
    - WWQ, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 6)
    - Telephone/Conference Notebook, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Derecho Internacional Humanos, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 6)
    - Notebook #14, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Derecho Internacional Humanos, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - Notebook #7, Undated (Box 7)
    - Notebook #6, Undated (Box 7)
    - Calendar Notebook, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - DIH [Derecho international humanos], 1998-1999 (Box 7)
    - Calendar Notebook, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - Prensa Pervana, Undated (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 7)
    - Notebook #3, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Drank Robin, Undated (Box 7)
    - Calendar Notebook, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Mother- RW, Undated (Box 7)
    - Drugs, Undated (Box 7)
    - To-Do Spike, Undated (Box 7)
    - Imigration and Mujeres, Undated (Box 7)
    - To-Do Notebooks, Undated (Box 7)
    - Gay/Lesbian II, Undated (Box 7)
    - Gay Latino, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Women Series, Undated (Box 7)
    - Watsonville/Lat Pols, Undated (Box 7)
    - Narajo, Undated (Box 7)
    - Minority Ph.D.'s, Undated (Box 7)
    - Lat Pols II, Spike, Drugs, Undated (Box 7)
    - Hispanic Elderly II, Undated (Box 7)
    - Mixtece, Undated (Box 7)
    - Mujeres Valley, Undated (Box 8)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 8)
    - Benefactors II, Undated (Box 8)
    - Hisp. Benefactors, Undated (Box 8)
    - Healing II, Undated (Box 8)
    - Minority Ph.D.'s, Undated (Box 8)
    - Healers, Undated (Box 8)
    - Elderly Hispanics, Undated (Box 8)
  - Haiti/Dominican Republic
    - Dominican Rep., Undated (Box 8)
    - Haitian Refugees in DR Reports, 1992 (Box 8)
    - [El Estatuto Juridico de los Hatianos y sus Descendientos Nacidos en el Republica Dominicana], 1991 (Box 8)
    - Current Human Rights Violations, 1989-1992 (Box 8)
  - Ecuador
    - Ecuador's Golden Crop, Undated (Box 8)
  - Bolivia
    - Notebook 12, Undated (Box 8)
  - Colombia
    - [Post Mission Memo on Colombia], 1994 (Box 1)
    - Untitled Notebook, 2000 (Box 8)
    - Telephone Notebook, 1998 (Box 8)
    - Calendar Notebook (Box 8)
    - Calendar Notebook, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
    - HR in Colombia and Ecuador, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Notebook 15, Undated (Box 8)
    - Notebook 18, Undated (Box 8)
    - Notebook 1, Undated (Box 8)
    - Notebook 2, Undated (Box 8)
    - State of War, 1992-1993 (Box 8)
    - Colombia, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Dog Obed- Clark Smith, Undated (Box 9)
    - Calderon-Schotzhund, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 9)
    - Untitled Notebook, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Notebook #2, Undated (Box 9)
    - Untitled Notebook, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
    - Untitled Notebook, Undated (Box 9)
    - Guaviare, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Telephone Book, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Untitled Notebook, 1995 (Box 9)
    - Trip- Nov. 1995 (Box 9)
    - World Report Material, 1993 (Box 9)
    - Displaced Ecuador Refugees, 1990-1992 (Box 9)
    - Mobile Brigades, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Yondo-Bombard, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Telephone Notes, 1995 (Box 9)
    - DIH [Derecho international humanos], 1997 (Box 9)
    - 6th Division, Undated (Box 9)
    - Notebook #16, Undated (Box 9)
    - To-Do Notebook, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Colombia and U.K., 2003 (Box 9)
    - Colombia, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Colombia II, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Notebook #17, Undated (Box 9)
    - Telephone Book, 1997 (Box 9)
    - HRW, 2000 (Box 9)
    - Cliff #2, 1997 (Box 9)
- Publications, 1968-2012 and undated
  Publications primarily address politics and human rights issues, particularly in Colombia.
  - To Build Anew, 1993 (Box 9)
  - El Camino de la Niebla V. I, 1988 (Box 10)
  - El Camino de la Niebla V. II, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Directiva permanente numero 024 Julio 5 de 1995 (Box 10)
  - El embrujo autoritario, 2003 (Box 10)
  - Demobilizing and Integrating the Nicaraguan Resistance 1990-1997, 1999 (Box 10)
  - Camilo Torres, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Entre el dicho y el hecho, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Derechos humanos en Colombia, 1994 (Box 10)
  - The Paramilitary Strategy Imposed on Colombia's Chucurí Region, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Panorama de derechos humanos y derecho humanitario en Colombia, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Los niños de la guerra, Undated (Box 10)
  - Colombia: Recent Reports on the Critical Human Rights Situation, 1994 (Box 10)
  - ¿A quién beneficia la cocaína?, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Por mi honor, 2000 (Box 10)
  - El terrorismo de estado en Colombia, 1992 (Box 10)
  - FARC-EP Historical Outline, Undated (Box 10)
  - Mapiripán. Sin Perdón y sin olvido., 2012 (Box 10)
  - Colombia Politcal Violence: Myth and Reality, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Sendero de violencia, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Epitafio de los inocentes, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Poesía nueva de Ayacucho, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Panorama de derechos humanos y del derecho humanitario en Colombia: 1999 (Box 10)